A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, International Division, Office Files of F. Champion Ward FA565
Rockefeller Archive Center
Given the continuing economic constraints facing the Foundation and rising debt in developing countries, the Foundation shifted support under DCP to smaller scale community-based initiatives in the field offices. Thomas was also charged by the Board to increase the diversity of grantees, especially to favor populations “most affected” by the problems of concern to the Ford Foundation. The Foundation built on earlier efforts and sharpened its focus on women’s issues throughout the world, including shifting the focus of the population program to women' reproductive health and child survival.
In the 1980s, Carmichael and others, with strong support from Thomas and the board, continued the 1970s’ support of South African grantees for training large numbers of black lawyers and litigating sensitive cases in the South African legal system. Recognizing the multifaceted nature of discrimination in South Africa, the Foundation not only advanced the rule of law, but also strengthened civic organizations, women’s groups, and educational institutions. Further, it supported a number of activist organizations in the United States that were energetically advocating US governmental sanctions against South Africa and for private disinvestment. The Foundation also played a role in shaping US policy on apartheid through the role Thomas played from 1985 to 1987 chairing the US Secretary of State’s Advisory Committee on South Africa.
The Foundation's overseas staff also sought to improve the economic situation in poor, marginalized communities through targeted loan programs particularly to women head of households, beginning with the innovative work in Bangladesh of Professor Mohammed Yunus, the founder of the Grameen Bank. The results led the way to establish the field of microfinance with the aim of empowering women living in poverty conditions, such as through a microfinance network in Latin America starting 1980 and a global lending program for women starting in 1987.
Thomas encouraged staff to share results at worldwide meetings. During those meetings, Ford staff in the country offices and in New York tried to follow the mandate to work as “one foundation.” The persistent challenge toward meeting that goal, however, was that initiatives emerging from the New York-based programs, or indeed any program developed in one country, were not always adaptable, relevant or acceptable in other countries or regions. It remained a challenge to develop a unified program, despite the commitment at the highest level of foundation leadership.
Biographical / Historical
Segment 3. Period Summary - Transition and Restructuring 1966-1988
During this era, the Foundation’s earlier interest in business and the economy evolved into a commitment to improving conditions for people living on the margins of society. The Ford Foundation promoted advancements in women's rights around the globe and introduced micro-lending into grantmaking. At the same time, the economic issues that were shaping program strategies also affected the Foundation's assets. Severe cuts resulted in a significant restructuring of country programs and reduced budgets across all programs.
Even with the cuts in country offices, in the 1970s Ford grantees in developing countries received approximately 80% of the International Division budget. The remaining fifth went to Population, Development Studies, and International Affairs. Although representing a much smaller piece, the International Security and Arms Control program from 1973 was the Foundation’s most concerted effort to make meaningful inroads in disarmament and nuclear issues - those challenges most directly linked to the Foundation's historic concern for peace. By 1979, the Ford Foundation was the biggest funder of arms control as a field, both in the U.S. and overseas.
Biographical / Historical
Segment 4. Period Sketch - The Post-1989 Shift Away from Cold War Dichotomies
Between 1989 and 1991, dramatic changes in the external international conditions created a significantly different context for Ford Foundation’s international activities both in the United States and overseas. In November, 1989, the Berlin Wall fell. In February 1990, in South Africa, Nelson Mandela was released from prison. In December 1991, the Soviet Union dissolved. As a consequence, the Cold War was over, Western Europe no longer had a special strategic role in the Foundation, and program-related activities in Eastern Europe and the former Soviet Union multiplied. The Foundation not only continued the earlier efforts to fund leadership in the region; from 1990-1994, Ford also spent $1 million on the training of newly-elected parliamentarians in Eastern Europe and the former USSR. By 1993, half of the funds for grantmaking related to the former Soviet bloc were going to in-country individuals and institutions.
In 1989, Thomas also instituted a major restructuring of the Foundation to fulfill his vision of “One Foundation.” All programs were put into one division led by Vice President Susan Berresford. Carmichael joined the Institute of International Education to run a program on Soviet and Eastern European Affairs and then higher education in South Africa. All the Foundation grant programs - domestic and international - reported to Berresford: Africa and the Middle East (AME, formerly MEA), Asia (ASIA), Latin American and the Caribbean (LAC/OLAC), Human Rights and Governance (HRG), Education and Culture (EC), Program-Related Investments (PRI), and International Affairs (IA).
The change in South Africa opened up many new opportunities to work in partnership with a range of South Africa partners to promote and sustain the transition to democracy. The Foundation supported women’s groups working on law, development and reproductive rights. It contributed, for example, to the groups working on the Women’s Chatter in South Africa, resulting in the adoption in 1994 of the first constitution anywhere that specifically included sections on women’s rights.
During the 1990s, the promising political changes in African countries and elsewhere provided a positive perspective to counteract the continuing economic constraints facing the Foundation and the rising debt in developing countries. Both to reinforce local democratic initiatives and to address its economic challenges, the Foundation’s field offices across Africa and the developing world shifted their support toward the promotion of smaller scale community-based initiatives.
Thomas supported work on arts and culture, not as a goal in itself, but, instead, as a means for promoting social justice, education, and human rights, both in the United States and in developing countries. At the same time, while reducing support for cultural institutions in the United States, such institutions received support overseas to preserve and celebrate national and local cultural heritages. While in South Africa, for example, the Foundation provided support for Johannesburg anti-apartheid theatre groups, in West Africa it funded for nearly two decades a program to preserve and make accessible cultural heritage by expand the training of museum leaders and strengthening museum exhibit and outreach capabilities.
In the early 1990s, the Foundation through its India office helped establish an independent foundation to enhance sustainability in the arts community. Ford envisioned new opportunities for cultural institution to rely on local resources focus on new forms of creativity and encourage young artists, in particular. Similar to the Indian effort, the Ford office in Egypt in 1993 provided support for an arts-focused foundation.
When Susan Berresford became president in 1996, with a strong commitment to globalization as well as concern for the uncertainty it created, she reorganized the Foundation in to three large program themes that would inform grantmaking in the United States and developing countries: Assets with a focus on poverty, Peace and Social Justice on rights issues, and Education, Media, Arts and Culture to pull together related endeavors. She also created a separate communications program. Each program was led by a vice president. Berresford strongly reinforced the institutional and grantmaking goal of affirmative action, an organizational goal that had been initiated in the Bundy era.
She maintained significant support, domestically and internationally for women’s issues. She endorsed and encouraged the worldwide meetings staff members and grantees to continue to hold joint meetings in order to create a greater sense of partnership and shared purpose. The more promising international situation enabled the Ford Foundation in 1996 to open an office in Russia (Moscow) and in Vietnam (Hanoi). Berresford encouraged the development of local and regional peace and security programs in developing countries. A regional security, peace, and cooperation program in India, for instance, focused on the work of civil society groups as an increasingly prominent regional interest in South Asia.
In this period, the Foundation gave renewed the prominence of arts and culture in the US and maintained the commitment in developing countries. By 2000, funding levels for the Education, Media, Arts and Culture division were approaching parity with the other two, Assets and Peace and Justice.
Berresford also encouraged each of the programs to hold worldwide meeting to promote cross-program and cross-national collaboration in fields such as human rights, income generation, cultural preservation, and building capacity in the arts and arts management. One persistent question of such initiatives. Toward that end, and building on the earlier experiences in India and Egypt, Berresford worked closely with her senior vice president, Barry Gaberman and other staff to establish new foundations at the local and national levels, particularly in developing countries. Gaberman had been at the foundation since 1973, starting as assistant to the representative in Indonesia. After serving in a number of different positions, by 1984, under Thomas, he served as deputy vice president in the U.S. and International Affairs program. After the 1989, Thomas and Berresford appointed him deputy vice president. 1996, Berresford appointed him senior vice president.
As the twentieth century came to a close, the economic conditions of the 1970s and 1980s that had resulted in so much global debt, with special impact on the developing world, were slowly turning around. Many countries were experiencing economic growth and burgeoning democratic initiatives. Not only was the global economic situation improving but the Foundation’s assets were also growing. Consequently, the Foundation was in a strong position to bring attention to long-standing issues holding back developing countries. The grants programs addressed the pressing need both for advanced training of young- to mid-career adults living in marginalized and disadvantaged conditions along the equally, and for strengthening and building sustainability of universities across sub-Saharan Africa, along with enhancing broadband access for improved internet communications, promoting women in higher education, and strengthening postgraduate education.
Reacting to the tragedy of September 11, 2001, the Foundation provided immediate relief to affected local institutions in the United States. The Foundation also helped launch support a fund at the Institute of International Education to support scholars at risk in countries in conflict and under terrorist threats, especially in, but not limited to, the Middle East.
Biographical / Historical
Segment 4. Period Summary - The Post-1989 Shift Away from Cold War Dichotomies
Franklin Thomas’s presidency, lasting until his retirement in 1995, was defined by a commitment to connect the Foundation’s US and international activities around a few key themes. These themes were addressed through grants that created private sector partnerships, enhanced support for local community groups, and enlarged initiatives to promote human rights, with special attention to women’s rights. Throughout Thomas’s tenure, Ford staff reinforced his special commitment to bolstering marginalized communities and broadening access to the law and educational opportunity. The Ford Foundation led the way in building the fields of international security studies, arms control, human rights, and governance. Moreover, in this period, Ford was innovative in drawing together the fields of international cooperation and human rights into one program.
Susan Berresford in her tenure as president from 1996-1997 continued and expanded the activities she helped initiate under Thomas. She and her colleagues increased support for the arts and established a variety of major international collaborative efforts implementing the concept of one foundation. Ford staff in this period drew on the Foundation’s time-tested grantmaking strategies (supporting individuals and new institutions as needed), while concentrating on under-addressed issues and underserved populations. With Berresford’s encouragement, Foundation staff explicitly took into account the new global context, increasing opportunities for inclusion of disadvantaged populations in all of their activities.
- Subject Files, 1953-2002; I
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of alphabetically arranged subject files. Dr. Ward kept subject files for Ford Foundation grantees and grant projects and for Foundation policy developments. Other files concern matters of the Board of Trustees. Of note are the files on Vietnam, which detail the Foundation’s grant work in South Vietnam as well as policy changes instituted after the fall of Saigon.
  - Afghanistan Trip -- Notes and Memoranda Re: Research Project in Afghanistan, Mar 1978 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Agency for International Development (AID) -- Memoranda Re: Education Grants, Background, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - American Council on Education -- Correspondence and Meeting Minutes Re: Presidential Initiatives, Feb 7-Apr 25, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Asia & Pacific Concerns -- Memoranda Re: East Asian Libraries, South Asian Studies, Thai October Revolution, etc. (1 of 4), 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Asia & Pacific Concerns -- Reports on India, Japan, Economic Review, etc. (2 of 4), 1975 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Asia & Pacific Concerns -- Notes and Memoranda Re: South Asian Education, etc. (3 of 4), 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Asia & Pacific Concerns -- Reports and Correspondence Re: Trustees in India, etc. (4 of 4), 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - A&P -- Sri Lanka (Ceylon) -- Memoranda Re: Meetings, etc., 1956-1966 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - A&P -- Thailand - Memoranda Re: Meeting, etc., 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Asian Development Bank -- Report on Bank's Role in Education, Mar 1970 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Asian Studies -- Columbia -- Expenditures, Notes, Correspondence, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Asian Studies -- Cornell -- Reports, Correspondence, Expenditures, 1973-1975 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Asian Studies -- Harvard -- Notes, Expenditures, Memoranda Re: Site Visit, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Asian Studies -- University of California, Berkeley -- Report and Expenditures, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Asian Studies -- University of Chicago -- South Asian Studies -- Report, 1969-1975 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Asian Studies -- University of Chicago -- Financing, Proposal, Correspondence, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Asian Studies -- University of Chicago -- Grant Reports, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Asian Studies -- University of Michigan -- Notes, Background, 1974-1976 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - "Assistance to Education in the '70s" -- Manuscript and Comments, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Board of Trustees Docket, Jun 26-27, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Chile Trip -- Memoranda, Reports, Transcripts Re: Education, Notes, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Cultural Grants -- Memoranda Re: Policy on Overseas Grants, 1961-1964 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Cummings, William K. -- Correspondence Re: Appointment, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Education -- Meeting Agenda, Reports, Memoranda, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Education -- Memoranda Re: Program Strategy, etc., 1977 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Education -- Memoranda -- Dr. Reuben Frodin, 1975-1977 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Education & World Affairs (EWA) -- F. Champion Ward's Personal Files, 1961-1965 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Education Group -- Meetings -- Agenda, Memoranda, Background, 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Education Group -- Retrospective Language Survey -- Education Conference, Survey Background Documents (1 of 2), Jan-Nov 1973 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Education Group -- Retrospective Language Survey -- Higher Education Study, Consultant Reports (2 of 2), Dec 1973-Feb 1974 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Educational Development Corporation (EDC) -- Memorandum from Francis X. Sutton Re: EDC Study of Kenya's Educational System, Mar 11, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Endowment Grants -- Guidelines -- Memorandum, Feb 9, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Evaluation -- Meeting Information on University Grant Evaluations, Jan 5-17, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Gordon, Shirley -- Universidade Federal da Bahia -- Correspondence and Proposal Re: FF Project Specialist, 1970 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - India Ministry of Education -- Correspondence, Reports, 1956-2002 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Institute of International Education (IIE) -- Memoranda, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - International Association for Cultural Freedom -- Memoranda Re: Congress for Cultural Freedom, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - International Bank for Reconstruction and Development (IBRD) -- Re: External Evaluation of IBRD's Education Program, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - International Council for Educational Development (ICED) -- Grantee Report, Handwritten Notes, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - International Division Conference, New Delhi, India -- Operation Janus, 1961-1966 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - International Division Meeting -- Rapporteur's Reports, Sep 19-23, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - International Institute of Educational Research (IIER) -- Memoranda Re: Organization Plans, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - International Studies Review -- Memoranda, Reports, Notes on Grant Evaluations (1 of 3), 1969-1973 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - International Studies Review -- Memoranda, Reports, Notes (2 of 3), 1973-1974 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - International Studies Review -- Memoranda, Reports, Notes (3 of 3), 1975-1978 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - International Studies Review -- ACLS/SSRC -- Notes and Memoranda Re: Committees, 1973-1976 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - International Studies Review -- OE/ACE/IEP -- Memoranda, 1973-1977 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - LAC -- Mexico -- Separated Reports, Address Change, 1961-1965 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Memoranda -- Re: ICED, CIDA, Teacher Training, etc. (1 of 2), Feb-Apr 1971 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Memoranda -- Re: UNESCO, Canada Visits, etc. (2 of 2), Jul 1971-Jan 1972 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - MEA -- East & Central Africa -- Memoranda Re: Grants, Meetings, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - MEA -- Ghana -- FF Activities Resume, 1961-1966 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - MEA -- Jordon -- Arab Development Society Memoranda, 1962-1966 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - MEA -- Turkey -- Reports (separated), 1953-1957 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Minnesota, University of -- Site Visit Report, Feb 14, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - New York/Regional -- Proposals for SEA Grants, Pakistan Close-Out, 1976-1977 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - "Nuclear Power Issues: A Foundation Strategy" (report), Jun 1975 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Pakistan -- Correspondence Re: FF Support, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Personnel Recruiting -- Memoranda and Correspondence Re: Project Specialist for Indonesia, Jan 17-Jul 20, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Planning, Exploration & Evaluation at FF -- Memoranda and Discussion Papers on Grant Evaluations, 1969-1975 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Pontifical Catholic University of Chile -- Foundation Concerns -- Report, Correspondence, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Pontifical Catholic University of Chile -- Notes and Proposals (some in Spanish), 1968 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Population Council -- Memorandum Re: Financing, Jan 4, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Program Planning -- Memoranda, Discussion Paper, 1972-1977 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Project 87 -- Re: Grant for Constitutional Research, May 1978 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Public Policy Committee -- Proposals, Meeting Agenda, Minutes, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Representatives Meeting -- Notes and Meeting Materials, Mar 1977 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - SEAMEO (Southeast Asian Ministers of Education Organization) -- Memorandum Re: Paul Hanna Visit, May 7, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - SAFP (Southeast Asia Fellowship Program) -- Awardees, Forms, PR Information, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - SAFP -- Bliatout, Thowpaou, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - SAFP -- Nguyen, Cong An, Aug 8-12, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - SAFP -- Nguyen, Dinh Hoan, Jul 11-24, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - SAFP -- Nguyen, Hai Binh -- Correspondence, Jul 24-Aug 5, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - SAFP -- Nguyen, Mong Bich -- Correspondence, Aug 12, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - SAFP -- Nguyen, Thanh Hai, Aug 7-14, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - SAFP -- Phan, Vu Trong, Jul 31-Aug 11, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Social Sciences in Asia -- Program Papers, 1976-1977 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Stanford University -- Asian Studies Grant Reports (1 of 3), Mar 1975 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Stanford University -- Asian Studies Grant Reports (2 of 3), Jun 1975 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Stanford University -- Asian Studies Grant Reports (3 of 3), Jul 1975 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Trustee Project Papers -- Staff Papers for Trustee Planning Project on International Activities (1 of 2), 1976 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Trustee Project Papers -- Staff Papers for Trustee Planning Project on International Activities (2 of 2), 1976 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - United Nations Development Programme (UNDP) -- Memoranda and Correspondence Re: Meetings, Proposal, 1957-1966 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - University of Pennsylvania International Training Grants -- Correspondence, Proposals, Reports and Memoranda Re: FF Grants to UPenn, 1960-1975 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Vietnam -- FF Correspondence and Reports on Education Grants, 1973-1974 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Vietnam -- Correspondence and Memoranda Re: Fall of South Vietnam and FF, 1975-1977 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Washington Activity -- Memorandum Re: International Education, Feb 11, 1977 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - World Bank -- Memoranda Re: International Education, Background, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Ward's Words, 1963-1977; II
  The documents that comprise this series had been stored in three expandable folders which were labeled “Ward’s Words.” The papers, memoranda and other miscellaneous documents appear to have been gathered by Dr. Ward or a colleague for reference purposes. Many but not all of the documents were written by or sent to Dr. Ward. The original chronological arrangement was retained. Within yearly increments, the files have been arranged by subject.
  - Address -- "An Exile's Report" by F. Champion Ward, Feb 23, 1976 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - "A Note on Knowing, Acting, Making and the College Curriculum" by F. Champion Ward, Aug 12, 1970 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - "Aspen College" by F. Champion Ward, 1963 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Bellagio Meetings Re: Education, 1974 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Bellagio Meetings Re: Education Policy Development, 1976-1977 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Board of Trustees Education Paper, 1976 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Education Group -- Memoranda, 1974 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Education Paper -- Assistance to Education in the 1970s and Related Memoranda, 1974 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Education Reference Papers, 1974 (Box 9, Folder 9)